<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>A Null Record</title>
    <link href="https://blog.isimian.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://blog.isimian.com" />
    <updated>2025-11-13T13:17:11-06:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Jack</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://blog.isimian.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>The Real Scam: How the Elite Trade Your Money for a Fake Sense of Superiority</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jack</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.isimian.com/the-real-scam-how-the-elite-trade-your-money-for-a-fake-sense-of-superiority/"/>
        <id>https://blog.isimian.com/the-real-scam-how-the-elite-trade-your-money-for-a-fake-sense-of-superiority/</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/39/Gemini_Generated_Image_gkzoywgkzoywgkzo.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="politics"/>
            <category term="deepdive"/>

        <updated>2025-10-30T14:00:19-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/39/Gemini_Generated_Image_gkzoywgkzoywgkzo.png" alt="" />
                    TL;DR: The people at the top distract you with a small, free&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/39/Gemini_Generated_Image_gkzoywgkzoywgkzo.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: The people at the top distract you with a small, free “social perk” so you fight your neighbors instead of uniting against the people who are actually stealing your wealth and time.</p></blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 id="lets-dig-in">Let’s Dig In</h2>
<p>This isn’t about some conspiracy; it’s about the <strong>core mechanics of power</strong>. Imagine society as a giant, rigged casino. The <strong>House</strong> (the wealthy elite) takes a massive cut from everyone, no matter how hard you work. Now, here’s their masterstroke to keep everyone from flipping the tables: the <strong>Racial Bribe</strong>—or, as the sociologist W.E.B. Du Bois called it, the <strong>“psychological wage.”</strong></p><p>Instead of paying all their workers an actual living wage, the House pays one group of workers (historically, white laborers) a “wage” that isn’t cash—it’s <strong>status</strong>. They give them a <strong>fake, but official-looking, membership card</strong>. This card grants them a few perks: public deference, better-funded public schools, access to public spaces, and preferential treatment from the police and courts.</p><p>The real price of this “wage” is that the recipient must now constantly look down on the other group (historically, Black and other marginalized workers). By being taught that their real threat is the person next to them in the poor house—the one who <em>doesn’t</em> have the membership card—they stay focused on an imaginary enemy. The House knows that if the poor people of all colors ever looked up, they’d realize they share the same problem: a boss who exploits them all.</p><p>This “psychological wage” is the ultimate sleight of hand. It’s an effective mechanism of social control that ensures the exploited group remains fractured and angry at each other, rather than uniting to take back the time and money the wealthy are constantly pocketing. The problem isn’t the failure of the individual, but the <strong>failure of a system</strong> that is deliberately rigged to divide and distract.</p><hr>
<h2 id="go-deeper--never-take-at-face-value-anything-that-claims-to-inform-or-educate-these-links-are-the-receipts-and-come-from-reliable-sources">Go Deeper:  Never take at face value anything that claims to inform or educate. These links are the receipts and come from reliable sources.</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/64515/64515-h/64515-h.htm">W. E. B. Du Bois’s Masterwork: Black Reconstruction in America (1935)</a>
<a href="https://items.ssrc.org/reading-racial-conflict/beyond-the-wages-of-whiteness-du-bois-on-the-irrationality-of-antiblack-racism/">The Psychological Wage: Du Bois and the Rationality of Racism (Academic Analysis)</a>
<a href="https://www.learningforjustice.org/sites/default/files/general/Jim%20Crow%20as%20a%20Form%20of%20Racialized%20Social%20Control.pdf">Jim Crow Laws as a Form of Social Control (Explanation of the “Racial Bribe”)</a>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychological_wage_of_whiteness">Wikipedia: Psychological Wage of Whiteness (Concept Overview)</a>
<a href="https://socialism.com/fs-article/book-review-the-new-jim-crow-inherits-the-racial-bribe-from-slave-days/">The Wages of Whiteness: Race and the Making of the American Working Class (Book Review)</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Is Systemic Pollution Driving the Next Stage of Human Evolution?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jack</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.isimian.com/is-systemic-pollution-driving-the-next-stage-of-human-evolution/"/>
        <id>https://blog.isimian.com/is-systemic-pollution-driving-the-next-stage-of-human-evolution/</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/38/Gemini_Generated_Image_va03z0va03z0va03.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="science"/>
            <category term="politics"/>
            <category term="nature"/>
            <category term="deepdive"/>

        <updated>2025-10-28T14:52:11-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/38/Gemini_Generated_Image_va03z0va03z0va03.png" alt="" />
                    TL;DR: The significant rise in non-heterosexual identities, particularly in younger generations, might&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/38/Gemini_Generated_Image_va03z0va03z0va03.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: The significant rise in non-heterosexual identities, particularly in younger generations, might be a biological consequence of pervasive, human-made chemicals altering our hormonal systems.</p></blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 id="lets-dig-in">Let’s Dig In</h2>
<p>Forget the noise and the culture wars for a second. The conversation about gender and sexual fluidity is often framed as a purely social phenomenon: people feel safer to ‘come out,’ so the numbers go up. That’s part of the story, but it’s probably not the whole book.</p><p>Here’s the inconvenient truth: the numbers showing a vast increase in non-heterosexual and non-cisgender identification—especially among Millennials and Gen Z—are statistically huge. In some surveys, over <strong>20% of Gen Z</strong> identify as something other than heterosexual. This exponential jump is too big to be explained by just “social acceptance.”</p><p>Instead, let’s look at the plumbing. Our bodies are run by a super-sensitive chemical messenger network called the <strong>endocrine system</strong> (hormones). It’s the invisible boss that determines things like puberty, reproduction, and, critically, how our brains and bodies develop sex characteristics <em>before</em> we are born.</p><p>Now, imagine billions of tiny imposters are flooding that system. These are <strong>Endocrine-Disrupting Chemicals (EDCs)</strong>. They are in everything: plastics, pesticides, industrial waste, and even our food supply. They act like keys that almost fit the hormone locks—sometimes turning the lock weakly, sometimes blocking the real key entirely. For decades, scientists have seen these chemicals demasculinize male amphibians and fish, and cause reproductive problems in animals. This isn’t speculation; it’s documented.</p><p>In humans, exposure to EDCs (especially in the womb) has been linked to issues like genital malformations and, critically, changes in the brain’s sexual “programming.” These chemicals don’t cause someone to be “bad” or “deviant”; they simply redirect a deeply biological process.</p><p>The essential point is that we’ve polluted our own evolutionary environment. The jump in gender and sexual diversity may not be a sudden failure of character, but a systemic, biological response to a chemically saturated world. It’s not a moral choice; it may be the latest chapter in human evolution being written by the toxic compounds we’ve released into the environment. We should welcome our friends and ask deeper, harder questions about the air, food, and water they (and we) are forced to live with.</p><hr>
<h2 id="go-deeper-never-take-at-face-value-anything-that-claims-to-inform-or-educate-these-are-the-receipts-that-come-from-reliable-sources">Go Deeper: Never take at face value anything that claims to inform or educate. These are the receipts that come from reliable sources.</h2>
<p><a href="https://esmed.org/MRA/mra/article/view/6342">Endocrine Disruptors and Human Gender Identity: A Study on DES</a>
<a href="https://www.endocrine.org/topics/edc/what-edcs-are/common-edcs/reproduction">Impact of Endocrine-Disrupting Chemicals on Reproductive Systems</a>
<a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/656708/lgbtq-identification-rises.aspx">Gallup: LGBTQ+ Identification in U.S. Rises to 9.3%—Huge Generational Shift</a>
<a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC4805122/">NIH: Perinatal Exposure to Endocrine Disruptors and Behavioral Endpoints</a>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Endocrine_disruptor">Wikipedia: Endocrine Disruptor</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Standard Mold: How Uniformity Becomes the Ultimate Tool of Power</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jack</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.isimian.com/the-standard-mold-how-uniformity-becomes-the-ultimate-tool-of-power/"/>
        <id>https://blog.isimian.com/the-standard-mold-how-uniformity-becomes-the-ultimate-tool-of-power/</id>

        <updated>2025-10-28T14:34:16-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    TL;DR: For those in charge, keeping the masses uniformed and predictable—like standardized&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: For those in charge, keeping the masses uniformed and predictable—like standardized containers—is an essential, historical tool for control and profit, leading them to suppress anyone who doesn’t fit the mold.</p></blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 id="lets-dig-in">Let’s Dig In</h2>
<p>When you look at how the world is truly run, you see a basic fact: <strong>uniformity is power</strong>. Think of it like a giant machine. The people at the very top—the ruling class, the aristocracy, or the modern power elite—need predictable, interchangeable parts to keep their machine running smoothly.</p><p>This idea isn’t new; it’s a root idea that goes all the way back to the days when power meant having the biggest, best-trained army. A thousand soldiers with the same weapon and uniform are a single, powerful unit. They are a standardized component.</p><p>The same logic applies to the <strong>mass public</strong>, or the “lower class”. For the elite, the ideal citizen is a <strong>standard-sized container</strong>.</p><h3 id="the-container-economy">The Container Economy</h3>
<p>If you want to understand this on a grand scale, look at two of the world’s biggest industrial revolutions:</p><ol>
<li><strong>Shipping:</strong> What made global trade explode? Not bigger ships, but the <strong>uniform container</strong>. When every box is the same size, you can instantly move it from a ship to a train to a truck without wasting time or resources. It’s efficient, predictable, and scalable.</li>
<li><strong>Nationalism:</strong> The concept of a “nation” is just a <strong>uniform social container</strong>. It blends many different people—different languages, histories, and beliefs—into a single, central identity: <em>the citizen</em>. This uniform identity makes the population easier to control, manipulate, and use for industrial labor, political gain, and consumer spending.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="the-price-of-deviance">The Price of Deviance</h3>
<p>This need for a standard container creates a fundamental problem for the people who hold the reins: <strong>deviance</strong>.</p><p>Anyone who doesn’t fit the standard mold—the person who can’t be easily ruled, coerced, or manipulated by the usual tricks—becomes a problem. They are the parts that stop the machine.</p><p>Because the established tricks of control (like advertising, propaganda, or political messaging) don’t work as effectively on these “deviant populations”, the powerful have historically resorted to shunning and suppression. This is the <strong>root</strong> of why so many topics are made <strong>taboo</strong>. Whether it’s historical taboos about foreigners, non-English speakers, or the modern LGBTQ+ community, the underlying impulse is to suppress anything that breaks the uniform standard and, therefore, threatens the elite’s easy control. <strong>Uniformity allows for smooth control; difference requires messy effort.</strong></p><hr>
<h2 id="go-deeper--🔍-never-take-at-face-value-anything-that-claims-to-inform-or-educate-these-links-are-your-receipts-and-come-from-reliable-sources">Go Deeper:  🔍 Never take at face value anything that claims to inform or educate. These links are your receipts and come from reliable sources.</h2>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intermodal_container">Link 1: Intermodal Container - The Shipping Revolution (Wikipedia)</a>
<a href="https://soztheo.com/sociology/key-works-in-sociology/c-wright-mills-the-power-elite-1956/">Link 2: The Power Elite: C. Wright Mills’ Core Theory (SozTheo)</a>
<a href="https://courses.lumenlearning.com/suny-fmcc-intro-to-sociology/chapter/theoretical-perspectives-on-deviance/">Link 3: Sociological Perspectives on Deviance and Social Control (Lumen Learning)</a>
<a href="https://constitution.congress.gov/browse/essay/artI-S8-C1-1-3/ALDE_00013389/">Link 4: Uniformity and Power in Early American Law (Congress.gov)</a>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plan_for_Establishing_Uniformity_in_the_Coinage,_Weights,_and_Measures_of_the_United_States">Link 5: Uniformity and the Standard of Weights and Measures (Wikipedia)</a>
```</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Lily Pad Problem: Why Exponential Growth is Nature&#x27;s Sneakiest Trick</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jack</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.isimian.com/the-lily-pad-problem-why-exponential-growth-is-natures-sneakiest-trick/"/>
        <id>https://blog.isimian.com/the-lily-pad-problem-why-exponential-growth-is-natures-sneakiest-trick/</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/36/Gemini_Generated_Image_ddkv3dddkv3dddkv.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="science"/>
            <category term="nature"/>
            <category term="deepdive"/>

        <updated>2025-10-28T14:19:07-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/36/Gemini_Generated_Image_ddkv3dddkv3dddkv.png" alt="" />
                    TL;DR: Exponential growth is a deceptive mathematical pattern where small, gradual increases&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/36/Gemini_Generated_Image_ddkv3dddkv3dddkv.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: Exponential growth is a deceptive mathematical pattern where small, gradual increases suddenly explode into overwhelming numbers, which explains everything from viruses to the brief, massive swarms of mayflies.</p></blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 id="lets-dig-in">Let’s Dig In</h2>
<p>Nature loves efficiency, and one of its most powerful designs is <strong>exponential growth</strong>. You see it everywhere, from the fractal branches in your lungs to the structure of a tree—it’s a pattern of building on what’s already there. The key concept is that the amount being added isn’t a fixed number; it’s a number proportional to the <strong>current size</strong>.</p><p>Think of it like this: Imagine you have a pond with a single lily pad. This lily pad doubles its size every day, and it takes 30 days to cover the entire pond. The gut instinct is that the pond would be half-full on Day 15, right? Wrong. Because the pad <strong>doubles</strong> every day, the pond is only half-full on <strong>Day 29</strong>. That’s how exponential growth fools your brain—it starts slow, almost invisibly, then explodes in the final moments.</p><p>This is the power behind life, and sometimes, its greatest danger.</p><h3 id="the-pandemic-parallel">The Pandemic Parallel</h3>
<p>When a virus like COVID-19 begins to spread, it follows this exact pattern. In the first few days or weeks, it’s just a few cases. It feels manageable, like a few drops of water in a bucket. But if each sick person passes it to just two other people, that doubling effect is a ticking clock.</p><p>It’s the difference between simple, or <strong>linear</strong>, growth (adding one person every day) and exponential growth (doubling the number of sick people every day). Linear growth is predictable; exponential growth is terrifying because the danger is hidden until it’s too late. The system—our hospitals and social services—is entirely overwhelmed not by a sudden, massive wave, but by the relentless, geometric doubling that shifts from small to catastrophic in a flash. The crisis is not the failure of a person to get better, but the systemic failure to contain the initial, seemingly harmless, tiny growth.</p><h3 id="the-mayfly-swarm">The Mayfly Swarm</h3>
<p>Mayflies are a perfect, bizarre example from the natural world. These insects spend nearly all of their life—sometimes up to a couple of years—as nymphs, or larvae, underwater. They’re constantly eating and shedding their skin. Then, in a massive, synchronized “hatch,” they emerge all at once. The adult mayfly exists for only a day or two, sometimes just a few minutes, solely to reproduce.</p><p>A single female may lay thousands of eggs. This massive, sudden swarm of brief lives is necessary because the adult life stage is so short and so dangerous. It’s a calculated, mathematical gamble: by throwing overwhelming, exponential numbers into the air at the exact same moment, they ensure enough survive predators (like fish and birds) to complete the cycle. The mayfly’s brief, explosive appearance isn’t a miracle; it’s a testament to the brutal, efficient math of population growth. Nature is a billion-year-old design experiment, and these patterns are the peak of its destructive, beautiful genius.</p><hr>
<h2 id="go-deeper-never-take-at-face-value-anything-that-claims-to-inform-or-educate-these-receipts-come-from-reliable-sources-for-further-accurate-reading">Go Deeper: Never take at face value anything that claims to inform or educate. These “receipts” come from reliable sources for further, accurate reading.</h2>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exponential_growth">Link 1: Simple Explanation of Exponential Growth (Wikipedia)</a>
<a href="https://jonathanbecher.com/2016/01/31/lily-pads-and-exponential-thinking/">Link 2: The Lily Pad Story as an Exponential Metaphor (Manage By Walking Around)</a>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mayfly">Link 3: Mayfly Life Cycle and Reproductive Strategy (Wikipedia)</a>
<a href="https://populationeducation.org/why-its-important-to-understand-exponential-growth-in-the-modern-world/">Link 4: Exponential Disease Transmission and Flattening the Curve (Population Education)</a>
<a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/e/exponential-growth.asp">Link 5: Compound Interest as a Financial Example of Exponential Growth (Investopedia)</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Unbreakable Human Chain: Why No One is &quot;Self-Made&quot;</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jack</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.isimian.com/the-unbreakable-human-chain-why-no-one-is-self-made/"/>
        <id>https://blog.isimian.com/the-unbreakable-human-chain-why-no-one-is-self-made/</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/35/Gemini_Generated_Image_92zazr92zazr92za.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-10-28T13:57:53-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/35/Gemini_Generated_Image_92zazr92zazr92za.png" alt="" />
                    TL;DR: Every single thing we use, from a bottle of ketchup to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/35/Gemini_Generated_Image_92zazr92zazr92za.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: Every single thing we use, from a bottle of ketchup to the internet, exists only because of a massive, hidden chain of human effort, making our interconnectedness, not individual superiority, the true fundamental force in life.</p></blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 id="lets-dig-in">Let’s Dig In</h2>
<p>Look at the device you’re reading this on. It didn’t just appear. The materials were pulled from the ground by one person, designed by another, assembled by thousands more, and shipped across the world by another entire network. You are the <strong>inheritor</strong> of this object, not its sole point of value. The entire system—the thing we call the <strong>value chain</strong>—is just a fancy name for an endless line of people working together.</p><p>Before about a hundred years ago, getting simple things like a hot shower or safely cooked, clean food was either a luxury or impossible. These advancements weren’t handed down by an aristocracy; they were built by a collective of individuals like you and me.</p><p>The danger comes when we fall for the modern trap of <strong>idolatry</strong>. When you see a celebrity, a business titan, or a sports hero, you’re looking at a person who is fundamentally no better or worse than you are. They simply had more resources and leveraged a bigger network of other people. When you accept the idea that these people are “above” you, you’re buying into a conditioned mindset designed to make you passively accept all forms of authority—the police, the politician, the wealthy elite.</p><p>Understanding this chain is critical: it’s not an adversarial setup, and it’s not a default setting of the universe. It’s an undeniable truth. From the seed planted in the spring to the food on your plate in the fall, you can’t go one day without the work, effort, and care of thousands of other people. Every single person in that chain—whether they’re the CEO or the person loading boxes—has the same basic needs: family, home, and food.</p><p><strong>Unity, not isolation, is our default setting.</strong> We are biologically, socially, and economically linked. The air we breathe, the water we drink, and the biological matter that sustains us is constantly recycled in a vast, planetary system. That inescapable interconnectedness is our greatest strength. When you realize that the person at the “top” of any chain is just another link—no better than the person at the bottom—you start to build <strong>influence</strong> by focusing on the collective strength of your network, not by chasing personal, detached “power.”</p><hr>
<h2 id="go-deeper-never-take-at-face-value-anything-that-claims-to-inform-or-educate-these-links-are-the-receipts-and-come-from-reliable-sources">Go Deeper: Never take at face value anything that claims to inform or educate. These links are the receipts and come from reliable sources.</h2>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Value_chain">Link 1: Value chain analysis overview (Wikipedia)</a>
<a href="https://hbr.org/2018/03/the-interconnected-world-of-work">Link 2: The interconnectedness of labor in a globalized world (Harvard Business Review)</a>
<a href="https://ssir.org/articles/entry/social_progress_through_collective_impact">Link 3: Collective action and social progress (Stanford Social Innovation Review)</a>
<a href="https://ccare.stanford.edu/collaborators/common-humanity/">Link 4: The Universality of Human Experience and Shared Humanity (The Center for Compassion and Altruism Research and Education)</a>
<a href="https://cscmp.org/about-cscmp/global-supply-chain-perspectives/">Link 5: The evolution of the modern supply chain (Council of Supply Chain Management Professionals)</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Your Ignorance is Their Profit: How Simple Math Underpins the Elite&#x27;s Power</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jack</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.isimian.com/your-ignorance-is-their-profit-how-simple-math-underpins-the-elites-power/"/>
        <id>https://blog.isimian.com/your-ignorance-is-their-profit-how-simple-math-underpins-the-elites-power/</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/34/Gemini_Generated_Image_zfmk58zfmk58zfmk.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="science"/>
            <category term="politics"/>

        <updated>2025-10-27T18:13:21-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/34/Gemini_Generated_Image_zfmk58zfmk58zfmk.png" alt="" />
                    TL;DR: The wealth gap is less about grand conspiracy and more about&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/34/Gemini_Generated_Image_zfmk58zfmk58zfmk.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <hr>
<blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: The wealth gap is less about grand conspiracy and more about the deliberate failure of mass education to teach basic finance, turning everyday math into the elite’s most effective tool for control.</p></blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 id="lets-dig-in">Let’s Dig In</h2>
<p>The world is a complex place, but the bedrock of wealth isn’t. The real secret to how the rich get richer isn’t hidden in some secret vault; it’s in the <strong>math you never learned in school.</strong></p><p>The central failure of our education system isn’t that it’s too difficult, but that it creates a uniform level of unpreparedness for the real world, specifically in finance. While they taught you calculus, they never taught you how to calculate the <strong>true cost of your debt</strong>—the interest rate that acts like a relentless financial tide pulling you backward.</p><p>Think of it like a game of Monopoly where one team knows the rules of compounding interest and the other team doesn’t. You’re taught to chase status, buying “luxury” items that are nothing more than a temporary costume. This is the endless cycle of <strong>consumerism</strong>, which tells you that your worth is tied to what you own, not what you save. You’re buying status as a target for the next-higher social tier, but for the truly wealthy, these status symbols are <strong>incidental</strong>—they’re a byproduct of their wealth, not the source of it.</p><p>The rich, in contrast, buy <strong>assets</strong>—things that put money in their pocket. This is where basic math becomes a superpower. When you can instantly calculate the rate of return on an investment versus the crippling interest on a credit card, you see the game board clearly.</p><h3 id="the-landlord-effect">The Landlord Effect</h3>
<p>Your neighborhood, whether it’s the best or the worst, runs on the same invisible engine: <strong>land ownership</strong>. Real power isn’t in owning a fancy car; it’s in owning the <em>ground</em> that car drives on. Historically and currently, land and non-home real estate ownership are incredibly concentrated in the hands of the wealthy and financial institutions.</p><p>This concentration of ownership dictates everything: who gets credit, where businesses can set up, and who holds the ultimate economic leverage. If you’re paying rent or a mortgage, you are paying for their business model. They exploit the average person’s inability to do the simple arithmetic of ownership versus perpetual borrowing.</p><p>The root of this systemic issue isn’t the average person’s laziness; it’s the <strong>failure of society to provide an empowering, practical education</strong> that allows people to compete. When financial literacy is low, the population is systematically disadvantaged, making it easier to keep the wealth gap wide and the economic playing field dramatically tilted. The elite don’t have to be brilliant—they just have to be better at elementary-level math than you are.</p><hr>
<h2 id="go-deeper--you-should-never-take-at-face-value-anything-that-claims-to-inform-or-educate-these-are-the-receiptsthe-reliable-sources-from-established-bodiesso-you-can-check-the-facts-yourself">Go Deeper:  &lt;You should never take at face value anything that claims to inform or educate. These are the receipts—the reliable sources from established bodies—so you can check the facts yourself.&gt;</h2>
<p><a href="https://perscholas.org/news/financial-literacy-economic-mobility-tech-industry/">Link 1: How Financial Literacy Fuels Economic Mobility</a>
<a href="https://www.finrafoundation.org/sites/finrafoundation/files/Combined-Math-and-Financial-Knowledge-Tied-to-Better-Financial-Outcomes.pdf">Link 2: They Just Add Up: Combined Math and Financial Knowledge Tied to Better Financial Outcomes</a>
<a href="https://mellonurbanism.harvard.edu/rules-engagement-forming-guidelines-design-schools-working-marginalized-communities">Link 3: Land of the Free or Land of the Few? Local Concentration in US Landownership</a>
<a href="https://wid.world/document/global-land-inequality-world-inequality-lab-wp-2020-10/">Link 4: The Impact of Land Inequality on Economic Development (Academic Review)</a>
<a href="https://lawliberty.org/book-review/education-and-social-control/">Link 5: Education and Social Control (Review of Mass Education History)</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>You Aren&#x27;t an Island: The Deep Connection Between You and Everything Else</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jack</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.isimian.com/you-arent-an-island-the-deep-connection-between-you-and-everything-else/"/>
        <id>https://blog.isimian.com/you-arent-an-island-the-deep-connection-between-you-and-everything-else/</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/33/Gemini_Generated_Image_coezfscoezfscoez.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="science"/>
            <category term="politics"/>
            <category term="nature"/>

        <updated>2025-10-27T14:30:13-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/33/Gemini_Generated_Image_coezfscoezfscoez.png" alt="" />
                    TL;DR: The individual self is an illusion; we are all constantly changing,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/33/Gemini_Generated_Image_coezfscoezfscoez.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <hr>
<blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: The individual self is an illusion; we are all constantly changing, interconnected parts of one massive, recycled, planet-wide organism.</p></blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 id="lets-dig-in">Let’s Dig In</h2>
<p>Forget the idea that you’re a fixed, isolated <strong>island of self</strong>. You’re more like a <strong>river</strong>.</p><p>You start with the old philosophical puzzle called the <strong>Ship of Theseus</strong>: if you replace every single plank of a famous ship over time, is it still the original ship? That’s you. Your body isn’t static; it’s a constant construction project. Your skin cells are new every few weeks, and most of the atoms that make up your entire structure are cycled out over a decade. The average age of all the cells in your body is about seven to ten years—meaning you are literally a different collection of parts than you were ten years ago.</p><p>But the shift is bigger than your own body. Where do the old pieces go? Back into the system. You are constantly inhaling the shed skin and dander of other people, animals, and the world around you. You drink water that was once part of a dinosaur. The air you breathe is shared by every living thing on the planet. This isn’t a metaphor; it’s a <strong>massive, closed-loop recycling program</strong>.</p><p>This continuous flow means that the Western idea of the rugged, self-made individual standing alone is simply an incomplete map of reality. We are less like separate machines and more like <strong>fleas on the back of a shared dog</strong>—completely dependent on the health of the host and each other.</p><p>If your existence is fundamentally an interconnected process, then all those artificial walls we build—based on class, wealth, or location—are nothing short of foolish. Recognizing this universal connection, especially our unbreakable tie to the Earth and its resources, isn’t just about being nice to the environment. It’s about <strong>self-preservation</strong>. To harm the planet or one another is, quite literally, to harm a part of your own extended organism.</p><hr>
<h2 id="go-deeper">Go Deeper:</h2>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ship_of_Theseus">The Ship of Theseus Paradox - Wikipedia</a>
<a href="https://www.questdiagnostics.com/patients/blog/articles/do-my-cells-really-change-every-7-years">How Fast the Human Body Replaces Its Cells - Quest Diagnostics</a>
<a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/identity-personal/">Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy: Personal Identity</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Your Brain Has Two You&#x27;s: The Operating System and the App Store</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jack</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.isimian.com/your-brain-has-two-yous-the-operating-system-and-the-app-store/"/>
        <id>https://blog.isimian.com/your-brain-has-two-yous-the-operating-system-and-the-app-store/</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/32/Gemini_Generated_Image_dtd3ridtd3ridtd3.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="nature"/>
            <category term="deepdive"/>

        <updated>2025-10-27T14:12:27-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/32/Gemini_Generated_Image_dtd3ridtd3ridtd3.png" alt="" />
                    TL;DR: Your sense of self is a mix of your factory-installed “you”&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/32/Gemini_Generated_Image_dtd3ridtd3ridtd3.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: Your sense of self is a mix of your factory-installed “you” (the core wiring) and a heavily customized “you” (the social software others have installed).</p></blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 id="lets-dig-in">Let’s Dig In</h2>
<p>Think of your mind as a computer with two distinct parts.</p><p>First, you have the <strong>BIOS level</strong>—the core, factory-installed operating system. This is the <strong>“You Who Is Sitting Alone in a Quiet Room.”</strong> It’s your original, raw temperament: your basic need for safety, your innate sensitivity to light or sound, and the primal wiring that controls your most basic drives like hunger and sleep. It’s the silent, baseline version of you that doesn’t need applause or approval. This system is largely non-negotiable; it’s what your hardware is designed to do.</p><p>Second, you have the <strong>App Store Level</strong>—the personality you present to the world, the <strong>“You Who Imagines How Others See You.”</strong> This is your <strong>identity</strong>, a complex program built by years of external installation: your parents’ expectations, your culture’s rules for success, your religion’s fears, and your society’s need for you to be a productive worker or a defined group member (race, class, nationality).</p><p>Every expectation you feel—the need to stay busy, the pressure to buy a specific lifestyle, the constant anxiety over <em>not being enough</em>—is a heavy, high-CPU-use app running in the background. Your brain is a masterpiece designed to sleep from dusk till dawn, but the <strong>digital world’s apps keep it awake</strong>, demanding a response, an update, a validation ping. Your feelings of chronic anxiety and dissatisfaction are often just the sound of these incompatible, heavily customized programs crashing against your core, original BIOS.</p><p>The key to greater peace isn’t to reach some elusive “happy destination” sold to you by a commercial app. It’s to <strong>run a diagnostic check</strong> on your own mind. Figure out which anxieties are genuinely your BIOS warning of danger and which are just the loud, power-hungry apps that someone else installed to keep you running in their system. Once you see the separation—what you inherited and what you installed—you gain the power to start deleting.</p><hr>
<h2 id="go-deeper">Go Deeper:</h2>
<p><a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/self/">The Philosophical Concept of Self (Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy)</a>
<a href="https://www.verywellmind.com/what-is-self-concept-2795865">Self-Concept in Psychology: Definition, Development, Theories (Verywell Mind)</a>
<a href="https://openbooks.library.umass.edu/introwgss/chapter/social-constructionism/">Social Constructionism: Understanding Identity and Difference (Open Books)</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Real Divide: Are You Free or Just Following Orders?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jack</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.isimian.com/the-real-divide-are-you-free-or-just-following-orders/"/>
        <id>https://blog.isimian.com/the-real-divide-are-you-free-or-just-following-orders/</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/31/Gemini_Generated_Image_922tlu922tlu922t.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="religion"/>
            <category term="politics"/>

        <updated>2025-10-27T13:17:03-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/31/Gemini_Generated_Image_922tlu922tlu922t.png" alt="" />
                    TL;DR: The political Left fights to dismantle broken power structures for individual&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/31/Gemini_Generated_Image_922tlu922tlu922t.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: The political Left fights to dismantle broken power structures for individual freedom; the Right tends to defend those established structures in exchange for a sense of unity and order that often benefits the powerful.</p></blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 id="lets-dig-in">Let’s Dig In</h2>
<p>The terms “Left” and “Right” didn’t start as complicated philosophies; they started as a seating chart. During the <strong>French Revolution</strong>, those who wanted radical, sweeping change sat on the President’s left. They were the firebrands. Those who wanted to keep the old system—the king, the nobles, the church—sat on the right.</p><p>That simple divide is the key. The <strong>Right</strong> is generally the guardrail, committed to stability, tradition, and <strong>established order</strong>. The <strong>Left</strong> is the accelerator, pushing for <strong>reform, equality, and change</strong>. Neither position is inherently evil; one protects the valuable things we already have, and the other corrects the system’s flaws.</p><p>The problem arises when the established order is corrupt. When the Right becomes a shield for <strong>elites and broken power structures</strong> (like slavery, denying the vote, or allowing the wealthy to write the rules), the Left has to become a wrecking ball. The “conservative” position in that moment is simply to protect the powerful.</p><p>Think of it this way: You’re not a shareholder in the political “club” you’ve joined. Many people are tricked into supporting policies that actively harm them in the name of belonging. You may be one major health crisis away from financial ruin, yet you defend tax breaks for billionaires. You may value your independence, but you participate in a culture that demands you <strong>conform, consume, and obey</strong>—a culture that trains you to feel inadequate unless you buy what the elite are selling.</p><p>It’s not about wearing a certain political uniform. It’s about looking at a policy and asking: <strong>Does this serve the actual people in their daily lives, or does it only protect the interests of those already at the top?</strong> When you choose a political position, you’re not joining a team; you’re deciding how much <strong>individual freedom</strong> matters versus how much you value <strong>conformity and a rigid, powerful system</strong>. Know which one you’re really choosing.</p><hr>
<h2 id="go-deeper">Go Deeper:</h2>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Left%E2%80%93right_political_spectrum">The Original Left-Right Split (French Revolution)</a>
<a href="https://www.britannica.com/topic/political-spectrum">Core Differences: Equality vs. Hierarchy</a>
<a href="https://www.studentsofhistory.com/ideologies-flip-Democratic-Republican-parties">Understanding the Shift in US Political Parties</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Thorium vs. Uranium: Why the Future of Nuclear Energy is Being Brewed in Liquid Salt</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jack</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.isimian.com/the-nuclear-future-is-liquid-why-thorium-reactors-matter/"/>
        <id>https://blog.isimian.com/the-nuclear-future-is-liquid-why-thorium-reactors-matter/</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/30/Gemini_Generated_Image_h4tcpjh4tcpjh4tc.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="science"/>

        <updated>2025-10-24T22:15:33-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/30/Gemini_Generated_Image_h4tcpjh4tcpjh4tc.png" alt="" />
                    TL;DR: The next generation of nuclear power involves reactors running on abundant,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.isimian.com/media/posts/30/Gemini_Generated_Image_h4tcpjh4tcpjh4tc.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <blockquote>
<p>TL;DR: The next generation of nuclear power involves reactors running on abundant, liquid thorium salt, making them inherently safer and harder to weaponize than today’s uranium reactors.</p></blockquote>
<hr>
<h2 id="lets-dig-in">Let’s Dig In</h2>
<p>The established way of running nuclear power uses <strong>Uranium</strong>—think of it as the solid fuel rod of the energy world. This method is powerful, but it has bottlenecks: Uranium is limited, the high-pressure design risks a meltdown if cooling fails, and the process can leave behind material that feeds proliferation concerns.</p><p>The alternative is <strong>Thorium</strong>, which is four times more common in the Earth’s crust, often just leftover industrial product. Thorium isn’t easy to split (it’s <em>fertile</em>, not <em>fissile</em>), but when it absorbs a neutron, it transforms into the highly usable fuel, Uranium-233.</p><p>The trick to unlocking Thorium is the <strong>Molten Salt Reactor (MSR)</strong>. This design ditches the solid fuel rods for fuel dissolved directly into a hot, liquid salt mixture. This liquid core is the game-changer because it manages safety and efficiency completely differently:</p><ol>
<li><strong>Inherent Safety:</strong> This setup operates at low pressure. If the system overheats, a simple <strong>freeze plug</strong> melts, allowing the liquid fuel to drain by gravity into a safe, passive holding tank where the reaction simply stops. It’s <em>fail-safe</em>—power isn’t needed to keep it safe.</li>
<li><strong>Clean Run:</strong> The liquid state allows for continuous cleaning, removing waste products as you run. This maximizes fuel burn-up and drastically reduces the volume and lifespan of the final waste.</li>
<li><strong>Geopolitical Edge:</strong> Crucially, this cycle generates less material usable for weapons, making it an attractive, independent power source for nations looking to stay out of the nuclear weapon supply chain drama. While this concept has been studied for decades—the <strong>Molten Salt Reactor Experiment (MSRE)</strong> ran successfully in the U.S. in the 1960s—the current push is seeing global leadership shift, with countries like China aggressively building them now. The vision of limitless, cleaner energy fueled by this “industrial waste” is why experts like those discussing the topic in presentations like the one found here <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uK367T7h6ZY">The Vision for Thorium Fuel</a> see this as the primary evolution beyond current technology.</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<h2 id="go-deeper">Go Deeper:</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.iaea.org/newscenter/news/what-are-molten-salt-reactors">IAEA: What are Molten Salt Reactors (MSRs)?</a>
<a href="https://world-nuclear.org/information-library/current-and-future-generation/thorium">World Nuclear Association: Thorium</a>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Molten-salt_reactor">Molten-salt reactor - Wikipedia</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
